{"tossups": [{"question": "A city in this country\u2019s northwest was once the seat of Usman dan Fodio\u2019s Sokoto Caliphate. Enugu was the capital of a breakaway state in this country\u2019s Igbo-dominated southeast. In 1956, oil was discovered in Oloibiri near this country\u2019s city of Port Harcourt. This country\u2019s town of Chibok was the site of a 2014 incident in which 276 schoolgirls were kidnapped by Boko Haram. In 1991, this country moved its capital from the port city of Lagos. For the point, name this most populous country in Africa, with capital Abuja.", "answer": "Federal Republic of<b> Nigeria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This nation was targeted by Operation Meetinghouse, the deadliest single air raid in history. Curtis LeMay introduced incendiary bombing of this nation. Operation Matterhorn targeted this country from bases in India and China, and many missions to attack this country took off from the Mariana Islands, captured as part of the island hopping strategy. For the point, name this country, the site of the Doolittle air raids on Tokyo.", "answer": "Empire of<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Attempts to mitigate this event were opposed by Charles Trevelyan, who viewed it as a judgement of God. People escaping this event utilized both the McCorkell line and a number of \u201ccoffin ships.\u201d The Poor Laws were legislated to aid victims of this event, which prompted Robert Peel to repeal the Corn Laws. The fungus<em> Phytophthora infestans</em> triggered, for the point, what 1840s event in which a million peasants on a British island died, due to a massive failure of a staple crop?", "answer": "<b> Irish Potato Famine</b> (accept<b> An Gorta M\u00b4or</b>; accept descriptive answers that mention those 3 ideas; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A city in this modern-day country was ruled by kings known as Sapas and used a city plan laid out in the shape of a puma. A culture based in this country built the Puquios underground aqueduct system and left behind a series of lines that resemble animals. Quechua [ketch-wah] was a language spoken by a an empire based in this country that was ruled by Atahualpa. For the point, name this home country of the Nazca culture, the Cusco kingdom, and the Inca empire.", "answer": "<b> Peru</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler won a homeland succession crisis against Joanna, the daughter of Henry IV. This queen patronized the religious reforms of Francisco Jimenez de Cisneros, who pushed this queen and her spouse, to issue the Alhambra Decree expelling Jews from their realm. Christopher Columbus successfully appealed to this ruler for funds in order to finance his expeditions to the New World. For the point, name this Catholic ruler of Castile who ruled Spain alongside her husband, Ferdinand of Aragon.", "answer": "<b> Isabella</b> I of Castile", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At this battle, Herman Melville\u2019s character Israel Potter suffered numerous wounds. After declining command, Major General Joseph Warren was killed and his body desecrated at this battle. Thomas Gage was replaced by William Howe shortly after this battle, in which Israel Putnam gave the legendary order\u201cdon\u2019t fire until you see the whites of their eyes.\u201d For the point, name this June 1775 Revolutionary War battle, where the brunt of fighting took place on Breed\u2019s Hill near Boston.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Bunker Hill</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A medical shortage of this element was averted following a discovery in Tanzania in June 2016. This element can form Rollin films when it is cooled into a superfluid state. William Ramsay first discovered this element on Earth; it had earlier been observed by Pierre Jansen in the spectral lines of a solar eclipse in 1868. For the point, name this second most abundant element in the universe, the lightest noble gas.", "answer": "<b> helium</b> (or<b> He</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "In the lead-up to this event, one diplomat confronted Valerian Zorin over pictures of SS4s [\u201ds s fours\u201d] and R14s [\u201dr fourteens\u201d], declaring that he would wait for an answer until \u201chell freezes over.\u201d This event was resolved with a secret agreement to remove Jupiter systems from Turkey and the establishment of a hotline between Washington and Moscow. For the point, name this 1962 Cold War confrontation between the United States and the Soviet Union after the latter attempted to place weapons on a Caribbean island.", "answer": "<b> Cuban Missile Crisis</b> (accept descriptive answers and equivalents; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This company\u2019s funding of anti-climate change policy groups was the focus of<em> Mother Jones</em>\u2019 2005 report \u201cSome Like it Hot.\u201d This company, led for over a decade by Rex Tillerson, formed in a 1999 merger between its two namesakes, one of which owned the<em> Valdez</em> tanker that spilled tens of millions of gallons of oil off the Alaska coast. Donald Trump\u2019s nominee for Secretary of State served as CEO of, for the point, what massive oil and gas company headquartered in Texas?", "answer": "<b> ExxonMobil</b> Corporation (prompt on either half)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. This conflict began when 200 of Lentulus Batiatus\u2019 men escaped from Capua and ended when one side was forced into a last stand by the Siler River. Gaius Glaber was surprised by troops rappelling down vines on Mount Vesuvius during this conflict. Crassus ordered the losers of this conflict to be crucified and displayed along the Appian Way. For the point, name this first century BC slave uprising in which a former gladiator led troops against the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Spartacus</b>\u2019 uprising (or rebellion, revolt, etc.; accept descriptive answers involving<b> Spartacus</b>; accept<b> Third Servile</b> War; prompt on Servile War; prompt on Gladiator War before gladiator is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In April 2016, this politician announced that former CEO of Hewlett Packard Carly Fiorina would be his running mate. This man instructed \u201cvote your conscience\u201d in an early refusal to endorse Donald Trump, who trumpeted<em> The National Enquirer</em>\u2019s speculation that this politician\u2019s father was associated with Lee Harvey Oswald. For the point, name this Texas Senator, candidate in the 2016 Republican Presidential primaries, and according to his political opponents, a suspect in the Zodiac Killer case.", "answer": "Ted<b> Cruz</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country negotiated the Agreed Framework with the United States and was the subject of the Sunshine Policy. A famine in this country was called the Arduous March. One leader of this nation created a policy of self-reliance called<em> juche</em>, and this nation channels its resources into the military in a policy known as<em> songun</em>. This country\u2019s former leaders are described as \u201cEternal Presidents\u201d in their cults of personality. For the point, name this Asian country that has been dominated by the Kim family.", "answer": "<b> North Korea</b> (or the<b> Democratic People\u2019s Republic of Korea</b> or<b> DPRK</b>; prompt on Korea)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A controversy about this film concerned the depiction of William Murdoch as the shooter of Tommy Ryan. A subplot in this film involves the Bill Paxton-played treasure hunter Brock Lovett. This movie tied<em> Ben-Hur</em> for the most Oscar wins and, until the same director\u2019s<em> Avatar</em>, was the highest-grossing film of all time. The tragic love of Rose and Jack, who freezes to death, is told in, for the point, what film starring Kate Winslet and Leonardo DiCaprio about a famous 1912 shipwreck?", "answer": "<b> Titanic</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Late in this monarch\u2019s reign, he was advised by the Comte de Maurepas [kohmt de moor-pah], who appointed Turgot [tur-goh] as a naval minister and controller of finances. After this man\u2019s profile was recognized from currency, he was captured with his family near the town of Varennes [vah-ren]. This king was forced to convene the Estates General for the first time in over one hundred and fifty years, shortly before he was imprisoned alongside his wife, Marie Antoinette. For the point, name this king who was guillotined during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Louis XVI</b> [sixteenth]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This author was inspired to write a novel about the suicidal John Flory by the five years he spent as a policeman in colonial Burma. This man described his time fighting in the POUM militia during the Spanish Civil War in his book<em> Homage to Catalonia</em>. The island of Britain is renamed Airstrip One in another novel by this man in which Winston Smith is tormented by posters announcing \u201cBig Brother is Watching You.\u201d For the point, name this author of<em> 1984</em>.", "answer": "George<b> Orwell</b> (or Eric Arthur<b> Blair</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "During the development of this location, Walter Reed led efforts to combat malaria and yellow fever. The development of this location was allowed by the terms of the Hay-Bunau-Varilla Treaty, establishing a zone that includes Lake Gatun and was relinquished by the United States in 1999. For the point, name this man-made Central American waterway.", "answer": "<b> Panama Canal</b> (prompt on Panama)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s refusal to give up port cities led to the formation of the League of Cambrai. A ninety-year-old leader of this city, Enrico Dandolo, forced the Fourth Crusade to sack Zara and Constantinople after the crusaders could not pay him. This city\u2019s Council of Ten elected the ruling Doge, and its Arsenale [ar-sen-ah-lay] made it a naval power in the Mediterranean. For the point, name this \u201cMost Serene\u201dItalian republic, a wealthy medieval city built around a series of canals.", "answer": "Most Serene Republic of<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Construction of this city\u2019s Cairo Hotel led to the passage of the 1910 Height of Buildings Act. Its boundaries were surveyed with the help of free African-American Benjamin Banneker, and it was founded just downstream of the pre-existing settlement of Georgetown.This city\u2019s K Street is home to numerous lobbying firms. Pierre L\u2019Enfant planned, for the point, what city along the Potomac River, in which Pennsylvania Avenue connects the Capitol and the White House?", "answer": "<b> Washington</b>, D.C. (accept the<b> District of Columbia</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Jean Rey [zhon ray] fought to increase the power of this group and developed its budgetary process. This group oversaw the passage of the Schengen Agreement, which provided for decreased border controls. It was conceived as a merger between a series of communities for atomic energy, economic, and coal and steel communities. This organization was founded with the Treaty of Maastricht. For the point, name this bloc of European states from which the UK plans to withdraw as a result of the Brexit vote.", "answer": "<b> E</b>uropean<b> U</b>nion <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this war\u2019s Second Battle of Chuenpi, held at the mouth of the Humen Strait, the<em> Nemesis</em> became known as the \u201cdevil ship.\u201d The second of these wars began with the seizure of the<em> Arrow</em> and resulted in several nations gaining most favored nation status. Commissioner Lin, the viceroy of Guangdong, began the first of these wars by dumping an illicit good into the port at Canton. For the point, name these wars fought between Britain and Qing Dynasty China over the namesake drug.", "answer": "<b> Opium</b> Wars (or the<b> Anglo-Chinese</b> Wars)", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}